why not the volley with a forehand grip
i tell you yeah go ahead and tell me i
gave it a good thought go ahead yeah
sure because what i do this is a fourth
grip yeah so i just do that and it's
much easier much easier
it's no good right like this
okay so what do you do when you get a
low ball with a forehand grip how do you
do it
when you get a low volley with a
forehand grip what do you do
so
you don't you just
you just ignore them because what
happens when the ball is up high okay
fine you can pro you can probably get
away with this even though it's not it's
not optimal because you won't be able to
get any slice on your valley with this
grip unless you start turning your wrist
so in a low ball so you can't have the
racket closed like this so you'll have
to open it up to get the ball over you
have to bend your wrist this way and you
won't be able to volley at all
so you have
really big limitations with a forehand
grip on the body and on the backhand
valley as well if you the forehand grip
on the back of it the racket face is too
open
so you have to
learn to bend the wrist backwards like
this on the valley
to bend it backwards but i'm gonna i'm
gonna show you a way today to valley
that's like super uh intuitive
basically
it's gonna be like volleying with your
hands
okay so what i want you to do is yeah so
i want you to do this look put your put
your hand like this and grip the racket
with these two fingers
on the side like this yes and and you're
going to put the three fingers on the
strings yeah so it's going to feel like
as if you were
vowing with your hand like this yeah
right and by the way this is a
continental grip
it's not a forehand grip so you already
you see what i mean it's a continental
grip so you just put your hand like this
as well just grab the racket and then
all i want you to do is just tap the
ball like this let's try it out you go
right there hold it this way yeah
it is because you know you you need to
learn you need to know how to volley
even though you like being at the
baseline you might end up at the net
you know let's say by accident so you
need to know how to volley here we go
good very nice
there it is anna and again
perfect
hold the racket there that's it
good job nice
oh again
now you're hitting a biomechanically
sound valley that's exactly how you're
going to do it it's a little bit
uncomfortable so now
what i want you to do is go down on your
grip a little bit not all the way though
not all the way okay so you go
you go a little higher
even higher right there i hold it like
that and i'll do the same thing you're
going to put it here
because what i want you to do now is
because i'm putting your hand up higher
i want the actual impact of the ball to
be closer to your body so you can feel
it more so it feels more
like uh as if you're playing with the
olive with your hand yeah okay because
when you play the valley with your hand
you get a better feeling for it so hold
it here for a little bit and do the same
thing just go like that
good
come again
open the racket face a little bit so the
ball jumps up don't have it so neutral
open it just lightly like this so the
ball slightly goes
upwards good
again
good nice nice work
nice work
okay
come again
good
what's wrong with me i need uh i i check
i think
perfect anna nice
that's it that's beautiful right there
good
keep the racket there don't bring it
down keep it there lock it in
good yes
nice
and again
all right now let's go all the way down
to the continental grip
okay you're gonna go all the way down to
the continental
there you go and now you do the same
thing there you go like this
okay yeah like that yes that's it
a little bit not a little bit open just
a little bit open
yes
and again
good stable with your feet like i don't
want you like falling over like
stability
no i don't step either like stability is
super important if you wobbly your
contact won't be stable so not only do
you need stability with your hand but
you need stability with your body keep
your body still on the volley you have a
wide base be like a tree in the ground
like be super stable as you're violin
that's going to make your hand more
stable
all right
good and again come on
good
another one
excellent work
anna this is perfect
good keep the racket up a little bit
more a little bit higher
good
and again come on
it's a little too low that contact
there goes again
no no you framed it what do you think
was wrong on that one
you don't know you hit it here you hit
on the bottom of the frame do you feel
that
maybe yeah something is off i just don't
know what you didn't know you hit it
here
okay so you made a you kind of reached
this way and you made the contact here
like you don't need to extend the arm
this way at all
you don't need to go like this this is
the first thing thing people have when
they valley and the ball goes there they
stretch their arm out and go like this
move your whole body to the ball okay
on a whole bot not go like don't go like
this the whole body goes to the ball
yeah
yes
you don't need to listen the step
but you don't have to you can't always
step there's no rule that you have to
step you do it according to the ball so
if the ball is coming right to you you
don't need to do anything
if the ball goes there then you need to
step
there's no rules for stepping this
according to what's happening uh what's
coming from the other side
here we go
come on there you go
and again
oh wow perfect valley
good one
and again
good honor
good anna come again
not bad
wow there was a firm one there
again come
good work
again come on
a little too much movement there did you
feel it yeah don't you don't need that
you just go here
you don't need any of those movements
again like this and you just go here bam
that's all you need
again you're hitting the bottom of the
frame anna
you're hitting everything down here like
this towards the bottom
okay you need to hit in the middle of
the racket
so you're getting your you're extending
your arm too much towards the ball
unnecessarily so just keep it closer
it's okay to have a bend in here the arm
does not have to be straight ana the arm
does not have to be straight here it
doesn't it can be bent
yes
wow that's it seems so crooked
it doesn't matter
it's fine to be crooked the entire
forehand valley is crooked who came up
with stuff like this what do you mean
like listen it just doesn't you bring up
an excellent point the forehand valley
is counter-intuitive because most people
when they do a backhand ballet it's more
natural look on the back and valley i go
here it's natural right see how my wrist
is neutral yeah so most people
have a more biomechanically sound
backhand valve than a forehand valve and
forehand valley you have to bend the
hand this way you have to get the elbow
away because
it's a crooked yes a little bit crooked
but we're learning it
and once you learn it's going to feel
natural right there you can keep the
elbow bent but keep it in front i lost
my grip that's okay you're doing this to
me what am i doing no because you're
what you're doing you're correcting what
i'm doing is two things i don't want you
to straighten the arm because what
happens in a lot of your volleys
always has been the case the ball comes
and you go like this and you straighten
the arm and now the ball the ball goes
in here
okay on this side of the frame
so what you need to do well i can just
move a little bit so it goes but you
don't want a straight arm on the valley
you don't it's just
no if it's worse trust me you want to
have a bent arm you want to feel the
impact closer to the body remember we
did the drill with the hand the closer
the contact is to your body the better
feel that you were going to have and the
better stability you're going to have
you're going to be stronger so you keep
it bent but the elbow has to be in front
of you okay so you can't have the elbow
back here like this has to be in front
this right here this is a forehand
valley i know it feels crooked but once
you get you
like this you bring up another another
great point it's not the worst idea it's
not the worst idea in the world to choke
up on the grip
yes even some pros do this
so like right
yes yes you could do this this is not a
bad method and the idea is again the
closer your hand is to the contact the
more it feels like you're vowing with
your hand the more feel you have and the
stability is actually better the longer
you make the racket the stability gets a
little bit more tricky so i don't mind
you choking up a little bit okay going
higher here we go come on
yes
okay i'm gonna try to rally with you a
little bit back up one step okay good
come on
don't panic it's gonna come back to you
don't panic come on
good
come on keep the racket head a little
bit higher
good anna yes my my reflexes are way off
and you got the wind behind you
here we go
okay another one come on
rack your head a little bit higher i
don't like it dropping like this keep it
up a little bit the main reason why you
want to keep your racket head above the
above the handle is a more solid wrist
position because when that racket face
straightens out now you get the wrist
bending this way and it's a lot weaker
okay and also when you drop the racquet
down too much a lot of people have the
tendency to when the ball goes low they
just drop the racket so when the racket
is up here and when the ball goes low
you have to bring your body down you
have to start bending so bending is
super important on the valley when the
ball is lower you have to get down low
okay adjust but i always made try to
maintain this racket angle okay racket
head above the handle
there you go you went like this come on
keep it up
and be still with your body don't be
jerky don't be hectic be still here we
go good
come on anna we got our rally with these
volleys
good
come again
another one anna come on why is the
racket bent backwards
don't do this parallel to the net
yes racket parallel to the net here we
go
yes anna yes
yes
nice
this is crazy what's happening right now
move that ball right there calm
good
again come on
good anna
another one come
excellent
firm don't drop the racket
good
okay we're going to do back and valleys
in a second so when it comes to your
body just for now just let it go
because generally what you want to do
when it comes to your body you want to
do a backhand valley okay
here we go come on like a tree wide base
good yes
come on anna
good
rack it up don't drop it
okay keep the rack ahead up
good
good come on wide base you see how i'm
look how i'm standing you see how stable
i am i'm not going like like here and
here i'm like stable that's the key okay
stability
good good
again
good
don't drop
rack it up okay good look
when it comes to movement you are going
to move a lot on the valley it requires
a lot of footwork but the actual stroke
when you're hitting should be stable so
in this instance since i'm heading right
to you i don't mind you're just locking
in this position and just being like
this the whole time okay just to
practice the being stable at the moment
of contact
excellent job nice
good anna
good anna go
all right now that's good enough the
forehand valley is perfect you feel it a
little bit in your hand
okay it's the muscles getting stronger
so now the backhand body okay
and let's let's test something because
i'm a little bit worried about your
elbow
do you think
see
well that's my worry because one-handed
backhand valley since you have a
two-handed backhand it all the impact is
going to be here so
i don't know maybe
eventually i think maybe you could do a
one-handed backhand valley but for now
for now let's do two-handed back and
valley well let's do the same
progression but actually with your left
hand
so there's gonna be a progression for
the two-handed backhand volley so you're
gonna hold with your left hand here okay
remember let go with this
and just volley like this with the left
hand all right same as we did before in
the four on the forehand side you come
right back to me okay
good
again
i'm catching as well look
i got good hands see
fast
okay all right now we don't have to do
any further you're doing good you
already it's kind of you remember it
from this side so now go down a little
bit
go down yeah go down to here same thing
maybe back up one step
okay
racket parallel to the net
open up a little bit
okay
i see i knew it was going to go bad you
first of all you turned the racquet here
and you closed it a little bit like this
right there that angle see it's pear we
grease this one well that's naturally
that's really what happens when you have
weak wrists the ball impacts the string
bed when it comes very fast and your
wrist kind of collapses so by doing more
volleys this will strengthen okay okay
so parallel to the net tip of the racket
towards the side vents like this and
slightly open
okay
good
oh my goodness
i'm glad i got out of the way that was
good reflexes i swiped it like this
anna what are you doing to me
you're trying to injure me here we go
find the right thing okay not so hard
come on slow down this is scary you got
a killer lefty forehand valley good one
more
okay now
let's let's do this okay we're gonna add
this hand
okay but we're gonna keep it here go
here go here
and put this one down and i'll do the
same thing
here we go
good
it's okay anna don't worry again
yeah now you're super stable you're
hitting it very clean so the key on the
two-handed backhand valley as opposed to
like a two-handed backhand from the
baseline is actually more
more force and more stability is coming
from your left side from the left hand
see a lot of players with two in a
backhand valley they use the right side
too much and they go like this so the
left the actual left hand will give you
stability so think of it more
not as a two-handed backhand but think
of it more as a as a lefty forehand
on the on the backhand valley okay
i remember don't think this on your turn
well that's why i'm scared that this
does not apply to the two-handed
backhand from the baseline it's not like
a lefty forehand it's completely
different okay this is just for the back
two-handed backhand valley
okay let go of the right hand
and i'll do it do it
okay one more time
okay now put the right hand on and do it
okay good
you see the difference
yeah okay that's it you got it beautiful
now you're probably thinking i know what
you're thinking this why nick why not
just have two two forehand volleys a
righty forehand valley and a lefty
forehand volley
you can't do that because you can't
switch the hands fast enough at the net
so theoretically it works
in theory this
could work if you had tons of time but
in reality what happened ends up
happening on the court is not enough
time so you can't well you can't switch
from one hand to the other so so if you
if you have the racket and you do a
forehand valley here and then you switch
here into a forehand valley on this side
there's not enough time so that's why
you need to be like this and do forehand
valley backhand valley you know it's
going to be a lot faster that way
okay so now let's try to rally a little
bit
alternating forehand and backhand okay
rally values remember you can still be a
little bit higher on the grip
even on the even on the backhand valley
you can be a little bit higher on the
grip choke up a little bit like this
good
again come on
firm
i know the racket is moving too much
come on firm it up
good
backhand
it's moving too much anna come on lock
it in please here we go come on good oh
here we go come on
and it's too much stomping too much
going on look at me see i'm stable wider
go wider yes
yes yes
backhand
come on wide
good anna
okay now
now you're going like this and this
now show me a ready position show me a
ready position
okay actually what ends up happening
with the ready position on the volley is
the following it's not necessarily this
see it's not this
because would you have to protect
against our body shots body blows
okay when the ball comes right at you
like this
okay so in that case the racket has to
be slightly turned like this
all right so it's not completely
pointing forward because this would make
it more difficult to react to a body
shot
right so you go here slightly see i'm
waiting
i'm not like this
i'm more like i'm more like this it's
the more natural way to do it so you're
anticipating what i'm anticipating a
ball
coming to my body i got to protect
against that that is the biggest danger
the biggest fear that volleyers have is
getting blasted
okay everybody's scared that i'm scared
of that too you saw what i'm how i am
with you vowing to me i'm scared because
you almost took my head off a couple
times so
the best way to protect yourself is not
actually like this but it's actually
like this why because now you got the
shortest distance to
this
because any time the ball comes in your
body you want to go here
like this now having said that there is
one weak spot
[Music]
it's a little bit on the left side so
when it comes to your backhand you just
go you just go like this now here comes
the weakness of the two-handed backhand
valley because you have two hands on the
racket
this left hand is in the way so if you
didn't have the left hand you would be
able to go like that so you have to be
when the ball comes at you you might
have to let go of the left hand and go
like this but here's one weak spot
that everybody has
and it's kind of like a
i call the blind zone on the valley and
so when the ball is coming
straight in the middle is actually
pretty
comfortable and pretty easy to defend
yourself if you have the correct ready
position you just go like this you just
go like this you do get a back end okay
but whatever if it comes right here so
it's in your upper body but it's in the
top right corner on right-handed players
now you can't go here anymore but you
also can't go like this anymore this is
a a weak zone
all right and this is where
where players get hit most of the time
they can't protect against this area
right here
there you go
come on
nice
all right good rally there
very good rally let's try it again back
back up a little bit
my backhand
good
see the worst thing you can do is wait
on this side for the valley remember we
talked about the ready position
here don't wait here because now you got
a huge distance to the back
right here is your natural position not
that much just slightly to the left
there you go perfect
good
good whoa
wow anna this is crazy
insane
what a rally
it's fun right
all right now one more test
now
we're gonna like rally a little bit from
the baseline i'm gonna bring you in and
then you hit a couple of hours in
transition okay so when you do clinic
like they never have you do drills where
you're like running to the net
we run we do one on the run and bali
okay okay and overhead so you're doing
you do do this yeah
i mean it's not like
you get too many because there's so many
people no i get it i get it
good
good anna come on up get in
there and avali
bali
wow
well i'll put you up listen this is a i
want to make sure that you understand
that when you're being stretched out
sometimes you have to extend your arm
okay but i was just saying in the
beginning that a lot of players when
they're stationary and they don't need
to stretch their arm they could easily
go like this they unnecessarily so go
like this but sometimes there's gonna be
circumstances in emergency situations
where you do have to stretch your arm
as far as possible and abolish
come on firm
no wobble up there firm
come on no wobble
good
okay
long lunging steps might be unnecessary
going like this you might be better off
doing a couple of small ones okay move
these three balls go back
good attack it go get in
and volley come on adam
come on adam keep going keep going up
this is looking good
keep closing up
anna this is killer stop
yes how about the continental grip
did you have continental grip yeah are
you sure no
i don't think you did i don't think i
don't think you did i think you have a
slight forehand grip hand come get in
there
and volley change it
did you change it
okay you got to find a way you got to
find a way to change it in here now
remember the easiest way to change the
grip if you connect the racquet with
both hands and then you change it with
the left hand yeah to flip it in the
same hand is going to be tricky okay
and avaliana change the grip
yes you changed the grip
beautiful job i saw it
very nice let's do it one more time okay
last one come on
and change the grip and go
maybe the best valley you hit today
excellent work it's time to continue
well of course but now you understand
right
do you understand now you started the
lesson you told me nick you know it's
like it's the continental grip is so
dumb it's much better with the forehand
grip what is your opinion now that
you're doing this one i think it's
better
yes
oh my god all right so i changed your
mind still crooked but it's a little bit
crooked like how all of this
retrieving yes it makes more sense right
yeah all right good job anna nice work
no more forehand grip on the valley
good and guys i want to give credit to
the creator of this forehand drill which
is really genius
basically where we put our hand
on the string bed and getting the feel
to be more like as we were bottling with
our hand it was my dad that came up with
this drill
very close to him
passing away he recorded a couple of
videos for me
with some tips on how to teach the
valley and this was one of them and i
think it's a genius tip and i want to
make sure i give credit to my dad
rest in peace that is not my drill
it's his
[Music]
is